Alright then gang, so I just recently released a new Claude Code Masterclass on netninja.dev which is a deep dive into Claude Code and how I use it within my own projects and I wanted to upload a small preview of that course here on YouTube so I decided to release a small chapter of it all about setting up and using a custom spec driven workflow because I think this small chapter sits well on its own and I also think it's a good way of working with any authentic coding tools not just Claude Code and I wanted to share it. So if you do like this small free chapter and you
嗨各位，我最近在 netninja.dev 發布了一個新的 Claude Code 大師課程， 這是深入探索 Claude Code 以及我如何在自己專案中使用它的課程。 我想在 YouTube 上傳一個小預覽，所以決定釋出一個小章節， 內容關於如何設置和使用自訂的規格驅動工作流程。 我認為這個小章節本身就很完整， 而且這也是一個適用於各種 AI 程式工具的好工作方式， 不只是 Claude Code，所以我想分享給大家。 如果你喜歡這個免費的小章節，你
If you want to learn more about the process and dive much deeper into Claude Code and Agentic Workflows, then definitely grab the full masterclass from the netninja.dev website. It's $15, but you can still get it half price using the promo code ClaudeNinja at the checkout. So I'll leave this link down below the video and now I'll just cut straight into the content.
如果你想更深入了解這個流程、深入探索 Claude Code 與代理工作流程， 請務必到 netninja.dev 網站購買完整的大師課程。 售價 15 美元，但你可以在結帳時使用優惠碼 ClaudeNinja 享受五折優惠。 我會把連結留在影片下方，現在就直接進入內容。
All right then my friends, welcome to a brand new chapter. And in this one I'm going to share with you one of the workflows I like to use when I'm working with Cloud Code in a project. And that is a spec driven development workflow whereby we create a high level non-technical specification for any new feature. Then we create a detailed technical development plan based on that spec. And then finally we use that plan to implement the feature. And by using a workflow like this, I find it keeps the model more focused on the task and makes any guesswork
好的，各位朋友大家好，歡迎來到全新的章節。 在這個章節中，我要與大家分享一個我在使用 Claude Code 開發專案時喜歡的工作流程。 那就是規格驅動開發工作流程——我們為任何新功能建立一個高層次的非技術性規格， 然後根據該規格建立詳細的技術開發計畫， 最後用這個計畫來實作功能。 使用這樣的工作流程，我發現它能讓模型更專注於任務， 並將對任何正在開發的功能的猜測
or incorrect assumptions about any features it's working on to a minimum. Now, the inspiration for this kind of spec first workflow came from a tool by GitHub called Spec Kit, which goes heavy on the philosophy of having a high level spec at the heart of AI driven development. But personally, as a developer who likes to be very hands on and stay firmly within the development loop myself, I think that Spec Kit makes me feel a little bit too detached from the whole process of adding new features. So I've stripped that process back.
或錯誤假設降到最低。 這種規格優先工作流程的靈感來自 GitHub 的一個工具叫做 Spec Kit， 它非常強調以高層次規格作為 AI 驅動開發的核心。 但就個人而言，作為一個喜歡親力親為、 始終處於開發循環中的開發者， 我覺得 Spec Kit 讓我感覺與整個新增功能的流程有點太脫節了。 所以我簡化了那個流程，
and I've come up with my own lightweight and much simpler approach, which makes it easier for me to add my own input and manage the process. And therefore, it hands a lot of that agency back to me, the developer.
設計了自己的輕量化且更簡單的方法， 讓我更容易加入自己的想法並管理整個流程。 因此，這樣做將很多的主導權還給了我這個開發者。
So throughout this chapter then, we'll be putting everything together to implement this spec-driven workflow. To begin with, we'll make a new custom slash command to help us automate the process of generating high-level and non-technical specs for new features. After that, we'll be using Claude Code's built-in planning mode to make detailed technical plans for implementing those specs. And then finally, we'll be using Claude Code's extended thinking mode along with the Opus model to implement those plans. And they're the three core steps involved in this workflow that we're going to be focusing on in this chapter.
在整個章節中，我們將把所有東西整合在一起來實作這個規格驅動工作流程。 首先，我們會建立一個新的自訂斜線指令， 幫助我們自動化為新功能生成高層次非技術性規格的過程。 之後，我們將使用 Claude Code 的內建規劃模式來制定詳細的技術計畫。 最後，我們將使用 Claude Code 的延伸思考模式搭配 Opus 模型來實作這些計畫。 這就是這個工作流程的三個核心步驟， 也是我們在這個章節中要重點關注的內容。
spec out a new feature, plan the feature, then implement the plan. You could also add a review step at the end of this cycle to review the code once the feature has been implemented, but that's something we're going to look at in a later chapter and we'll just focus on the first three steps for now. I'll also be integrating Git into the workflow as well, so that every time we start a new specification or feature, Claude Code switches us to a new branch. That way, if things do go south, we can just delete the branch and our main codebase remains untouched.
規格化一個新功能、計畫功能，然後實作計畫。 你也可以在這個循環的最後加入一個審查步驟， 在功能實作完成後審查程式碼， 但那是我們在後續章節要探討的內容，現在先專注在前三個步驟。 我也會將 Git 整合進工作流程， 這樣每次我們開始一個新的規格或功能時，Claude Code 都會切換到一個新的分支。 這樣的話，如果事情出了差錯，我們只需刪除那個分支， 主程式碼庫就不會受到任何影響。
strongly advise using Git and GitHub if you ever use AI to touch your code because without it, things can get really messy really quickly. If you're new to version control and you do want to learn about it, then I've got a big Git and GitHub Masterclass course that you can check out and I will leave the link to that below the video. Anyway, let's crack on with this workflow by first of all creating a new custom / command to generate specs.
我強烈建議在使用 AI 修改程式碼時搭配 Git 和 GitHub， 因為沒有它們的話，事情很快就會變得非常混亂。 如果你是版本控制的新手，想要學習相關知識， 我有一個很完整的 Git 和 GitHub 大師課程可以參考， 我會把連結留在影片下方。 無論如何，讓我們開始這個工作流程， 首先建立一個新的自訂 / 指令來生成規格。
Alright, so now we know about the general process of this spec driven workflow. Let's start off by making a new spec command. And this spec command is going to do a few things for us. First, it's going to generate a feature name and a branch name based on the input or arguments that we provide to the command. Second, it's going to switch to a new branch with the name it comes up with. Then it's going to make a high level feature specification based on our import and write that spec to a file inside a specs folder. And this specification
好的，現在我們了解了這個規格驅動工作流程的整體流程。 讓我們開始建立一個新的 spec 指令。 這個 spec 指令會為我們做幾件事。 第一，它會根據我們提供給指令的輸入或參數生成功能名稱和分支名稱。 第二，它會切換到一個以生成名稱命名的新分支。 然後，它會根據我們的輸入建立一個高層次的功能規格， 並將該規格寫入 specs 資料夾中的一個檔案。 而這個規格
like I mentioned before, is going to be a high level one, meaning it shouldn't go into too much detail about how the feature should be implemented from a technical viewpoint, but rather focus on the bigger picture and how the feature should behave from a user's perspective, I guess, including any edge cases and wide implications.
就像我之前提到的，將會是一個高層次的規格， 意思是它不應該從技術角度過多說明功能應該如何實作， 而是要專注於更宏觀的角度， 描述功能從使用者角度來看應該如何運作， 包含任何邊緣情況和更廣泛的影響。
So then, let's make this new spec command by opening the commands folder in the .claude directory and then making a new file called spec.md, which means to run the command later, we're going to type out forward slash spec.
那麼，讓我們開始建立這個新的 spec 指令， 打開 .claude 目錄中的 commands 資料夾， 然後建立一個新檔案叫做 spec.md， 這意味著之後執行指令時，我們要輸入斜線 spec。
Okay, so now we can start to flesh out this file. And the first thing I want to do, like in all the other commands we've made, is make some frontmatter for the command description and allowed tools at the top. And also to add an argument hint as well. So then let's start with the three dashes to go either side of this frontmatter section. And then inside those dashes, I'm just going to paste in three different keys and values. The description, which says, create a feature spec file and branch from a short idea, an argument hint, which
好的，現在我們可以開始充實這個檔案了。 我想做的第一件事，就像我們建立的所有其他指令一樣， 是在頂部為指令描述和允許的工具加上前置資料（frontmatter）， 還要加上一個參數提示。 讓我們從三個破折號開始，放在這個前置資料區塊的兩側。 在這些破折號內，我要貼入三個不同的鍵值對。 描述部分說的是「從簡短的想法建立功能規格檔案和分支」， 參數提示是
is the short feature description and the allowed tools which are read, write, glob and bash to switch to a new branch. So that's the front matter sorted and now we just need to write out the actual command itself and rather than me type all of this out from scratch I'm just going to paste this in and walk through it all with you step by step.
「簡短的功能描述」，以及允許的工具， 包括 read、write、glob 和 bash，用於切換到新分支。 這樣前置資料就設置好了， 現在我們只需要寫出指令本身的內容。 我不打算從頭開始一個字一個字打， 而是直接貼上然後一步一步帶你們看。
And by the way, like I mentioned before, you can get this entire command yourself from the GitHub repo for the course files. All you need to do is select the Claude snippets branch from the dropdown up here, then go into the commands folder where you're gonna see this spec command plus any other command that we make as well. So if you click on that command, you're gonna see all the content for that file, which you can just copy and paste into your own file. So then let me just paste all of this in and then we'll walk through it slowly.
順帶一提，就像我之前提到的， 你可以從課程檔案的 GitHub 儲存庫中取得這整個指令。 你只需要從上面的下拉選單中選擇 Claude snippets 分支， 然後進入 commands 資料夾， 在那裡你會看到這個 spec 指令以及我們建立的任何其他指令。 如果你點擊那個指令，你會看到那個檔案的所有內容， 你可以直接複製貼上到你自己的檔案中。 那麼讓我把這些全部貼上，然後我們慢慢帶你們走一遍。
First of all then, we have this summary at the top which tells the model it's going to be making a new feature spec for the application using the user input below, which we say down here is from the arguments. So when we run the spec command later, we'll be adding a sentence or two about the new feature we want to spec so the model can use that input. We also tell the model to respect anything inside the claude.md file.
首先，我們在頂部有這個摘要， 告訴模型它將使用下面的使用者輸入為應用程式建立新的功能規格， 我們在下方說明這些輸入來自參數。 所以當我們之後執行 spec 指令時， 我們會加入一兩句關於我們想要規格化的新功能的描述， 讓模型可以使用這些輸入。 我們也告訴模型要遵守 claude.md 檔案中的任何設定。
Next, down here, we go into a little bit more detail, outlining the steps the model needs to take using that user input, starting with creating a feature title in Kebab Case, then making a safe branch name for the feature, and finally writing a detailed markdown spec in the specs directory, which we don't have yet, but we will make shortly.
接著，往下這裡，我們詳細說明模型需要採取的步驟， 從以 Kebab Case 格式建立功能標題開始， 然後為功能建立一個安全的分支名稱， 最後在 specs 目錄中寫入詳細的 Markdown 規格， 這個目錄我們還沒有，但我們很快就會建立。
Below that outline, we go into each step in more detail, starting with the step one, which is to check the current branch for uncommitted or unstaged changes. If we have any of those, we tell the model to abort the whole process and instruct the user to either stash or commit the changes first. After that, we tell the model to pass the input arguments to extract or come up with the following values, a feature title,
在該大綱下方，我們更詳細地說明每個步驟， 從步驟一開始，即檢查當前分支是否有未提交或未暫存的變更。 如果有任何這樣的情況， 我們告訴模型中止整個流程， 並指示使用者先暫存或提交變更。 之後，我們告訴模型傳遞輸入參數， 以提取或得出以下值：功能標題、
A feature slug which follows the below criteria: lowercase letters, kebab case, only letters and numbers, replace spaces with dashes, and so on. Then, finally, a safe Git branch name with the following format: Claude forward slash feature forward slash, then whatever the slug value is, and we give an example of that down below.
功能 slug，需遵循以下標準： 小寫字母、kebab case 格式、只含字母和數字、將空格替換為連字號，等等。 最後，一個安全的 Git 分支名稱， 格式為：claude 斜線 feature 斜線，然後接上 slug 的值， 我們在下方給出了一個範例。
So then, once the model has extracted those values, the next step down here is for Claude Code to switch us to the new feature branch using the branch name the model just came up with. After that, we ask the model to create the actual spec markdown file and save it in the specs folder using the feature slug it just came up with.
那麼，一旦模型提取出這些值後， 這裡的下一個步驟是讓 Claude Code 使用模型剛剛生成的分支名稱 切換到新的功能分支。 之後，我們要求模型使用剛剛生成的功能 slug 建立實際的規格 Markdown 檔案並儲存在 specs 資料夾中。
We also mention here that we'll be using plan mode later to plan the spec, and we're going to talk about plan mode later in this chapter, but as well as that, we tell the model to use the same structure for the spec file as the spec template file right here, using the @ symbol to manually add that template file as context.
我們也在這裡提到稍後將使用規劃模式來規劃規格， 我們會在本章後面討論規劃模式， 但除此之外，我們告訴模型使用這裡的規格範本檔案相同的結構 來建立規格檔案， 使用 @ 符號手動將那個範本檔案作為上下文加入。
Now, we don't have that template file created yet, but again, we will make it shortly. We also tell the model not to add any technical implementation details, such as code examples, because that's what the planning step is for later. Finally, once that spec's been created, we ask the model to respond with a short summary of what it's done, including the branch name, the spec file location, and the feature title. So that is the spec command done now.
現在，我們還沒有建立那個範本檔案，但同樣地，我們很快就會建立。 我們也告訴模型不要添加任何技術實作細節， 例如程式碼範例，因為那是後續規劃步驟的工作。 最後，一旦規格建立完成， 我們要求模型回應一個簡短的摘要說明它做了什麼， 包括分支名稱、規格檔案位置和功能標題。 這樣 spec 指令就完成了。
We're gonna be using this in the next lesson to spec out a new feature, but for now, all we need to do is create that specs folder, which is gonna create all the new spec files in. And we also need to create the template file, because it's gonna use that file to create the specs, right? So let's cross this off, and then we'll create a new folder in the root directory called specs. And the only reason I'm using an underscore right here is so that this folder sits at the top of the tree, there's no deeper meaning than that.
我們將在下一堂課中使用這個指令來規格化一個新功能， 但現在，我們需要做的就是建立那個 specs 資料夾， 所有新的規格檔案都會建立在其中。 我們還需要建立範本檔案，因為它要使用那個檔案來建立規格，對吧？ 所以讓我們把這個打勾， 然後在根目錄建立一個叫做 specs 的新資料夾。 我在這裡使用底線的唯一原因是讓這個資料夾排在目錄樹的最上方， 沒有比這更深的含義了。
But inside that now, we're gonna create a new file called template.md, and I'm just gonna paste in this template. It's very, very simple, but I'll go through it. So we have the feature name at the top, then the branch name it chooses, and then down here, we say Figma component if used. Now, don't worry about this too much for now. Later in the course, we'll be using Figma, and we're gonna integrate that into the spec command. So we'll come back to that later, for now, we're not using Figma.
在那個資料夾裡，我們現在要建立一個叫做 template.md 的新檔案， 我要直接貼入這個範本。它非常非常簡單，但我會帶你們看一遍。 頂部是功能名稱，然後是它選擇的分支名稱， 再往下這裡，我們說的是 Figma 元件（如果有使用的話）。 現在先不用太擔心這個部分。 在課程後面，我們會使用 Figma，並將它整合進 spec 指令中。 所以我們稍後會回來看這個，現在我們先不使用 Figma。
Anyway, we have these different sections that we want Claude Code to fill in when it's creating this spec file. So we have a summary of the spec or feature, any functional requirements, the Figma design reference, only of referenced, again, don't worry about that too much for now, we'll come back to it later. And then down here, any possible edge cases, the acceptance criteria, open questions. So if it has any questions it wants to ask us, put them there and then we can go in.
無論如何，我們有這些不同的區塊， 我們希望 Claude Code 在建立這個規格檔案時填入。 我們有規格或功能的摘要、任何功能需求、 Figma 設計參考（僅在有參考的情況下）， 同樣，現在先不用太擔心這個，我們稍後會回來看。 然後往下這裡，任何可能的邊緣情況、驗收標準、開放問題。 如果它有任何想問我們的問題，就放在那裡，然後我們可以進去
and answer those questions, and then any testing guidelines at the bottom. And I've also said here, create a test file in the test folder for any new feature and create meaningful tests for the following cases without going too heavy. So obviously, I don't know the test cases. That's for Claude Code to decide when we're specing out the new feature.
並回答這些問題，然後底部是任何測試指南。 我在這裡也說了，為任何新功能在 test 資料夾中建立一個測試檔案， 並為以下情況建立有意義的測試，但不要過於繁重。 所以顯然，我不知道測試案例， 那是 Claude Code 在我們規格化新功能時自行決定的。
All right, so now we have the new command, this spec command, and we have this template, so that when it's creating specs, it uses this template. In the next lesson, let's create a new spec for a brand new feature.
好的，現在我們有了新的指令，這個 spec 指令， 以及這個範本，這樣當它建立規格時，就會使用這個範本。 在下一堂課中，讓我們為全新的功能建立一個新的規格。